{"tossups": [{"question": "Walter Jarboe operated a gang of mercenaries in this state, kidnapping Yuki natives. Despite banning African American slavery, this state allowed for \u201capprenticing\u201d of Native Americans in a form of slavery documented by John Ross Browne. In this state, Sheriff William Dixon massacred more than 150 Wintu people in the Bridge Gulch massacre. Slave labor in this state built New Helvetia, a fort owned by John Sutter. For ten points, name this state where many Native Americans were killed during an 1849 gold rush.", "answer": "<b> California</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A fleet of this country was captured by Piet Hein at the Bay of Matanzas, and George Rooke attacked this fleet at Vigo Bay in 1702. This country caused relatively high inflation in a namesake Price Revolution that was driven by trade of cochineal dye, silver from Callao, and other items regulated at its Casa de Contrataci\u00b4on. For ten points, name this European country that operated a treasure fleet of galleons between Manila and Acapulco.", "answer": "<b> Spain</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s uncle of the same name and his brother Stesagoras each ruled the Chersonese as tyrants. Late in life, this man suffered a leg wound while attacking the island of Paros; he was imprisoned for treason and died of gangrene. This man, who was forced to fight the Scythians under Darius, convinced Athens to execute messengers sent by Darius demanding earth and water. The polemarch Callimachus broke a tie on the advice of this man, leading to a decisive victory in 490 BC. For ten points, name this general whose strategy won the Battle of Marathon.", "answer": "<b> Miltiades</b> the Younger", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s son Pufang is an advocate for disability rights, having been paralyzed during torture by the Red Guards. This man consolidated power with the help of the Eight Elders, who met frequently at his home. This man worked with Zhao Ziyang to remove Hua Guofeng from the premiership, noting that\u201cit doesn\u2019t matter whether a cat is white or black as long as it catches mice.\u201d This man was criticized for suppressing the Tiananmen Square protests. Shanghai was opened to foreign investment by, for ten points, what Chinese leader who reformed the economy in the 1980s?", "answer": "<b> Deng</b> Xiaoping", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s daughter Mary played Kristin Shepard, who turned out to be the one who shot J.R. in the famous cliffhanger of the soap opera<em> Dallas</em>. This man, whose last TV appearance was on a Christmas special singing a duet with David Bowie, co-starred in a film series beginning with<em> Road to Singapore</em> with Bob Hope. A recording of this man was used in Operation Frequent Wind to signal the American evacuation from Saigon. For ten points, name this American actor and singer of \u201cWhite Christmas.\u201d", "answer": "Harold \u201cBing\u201d<b> Crosby</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This philosopher, who developed a method of steam distillation to produce rose water and essential oils, claimed he had read Aristotle\u2019s<em> Metaphysics</em> 40 times before reading a commentary by al-Farabi. This main target of al-Ghazali\u2019s<em> The Incoherence of the Philosophers</em> argued for the existence of the soul with the \u201cfloating man\u201d argument.<em> The Canon of Medicine</em> and<em> The Book of Healing</em> were written by, for ten points, what Persian Islamic philosopher of the 11th century?", "answer": "<b> Avicenna</b> (or<b> ibn Sina</b>; or<b> Abu Ali Sina</b>; or<b> Pur Sina</b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "The division of this man\u2019s empire between his sons alk-Amin and al-Ma\u2019mun caused a civil war. Before becoming a ruler, this man led an assault against Empress Irene, reaching as far as Chrysopolis before turning around. Twelve mechanical knights were part of a water clock that this man sent to Charlemagne with an elephant and other gifts. This man, whose epithet means \u201cRightly Guided,\u201d created the House of Wisdom in Baghdad, which became a center of learning during the Islamic Golden Age. For ten points, name this fifth Abbasid Caliph.", "answer": "<b> Harun</b> al-Rashid (or<b> Harun</b> the Orthodox,<b> Harun</b> the Rightly-Guided,<b> Harun</b> the Upright, <b>Harun</b> the Just, accept<b> Aaron</b> for Harun)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s reputation was hurt after attempting to cover up a leak of the military exercise Fallex 62. This leader declared \u201cthis is our breakthrough\u201d after a new plan to pool coal production with France was adopted in the Schuman Declaration. More controversially, this politician ordered the arrest of<em> Der Spiegel</em> journalists in 1962 after they had leaked state secrets. Ludwig Erhard\u2019s post-war economic revitalization took place under, for ten points, what first Chancellor of West Germany?", "answer": "Konrad<b> Adenauer</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This woman asked a series of 42 questions about scripture in a letter she likely wrote from the Oratory of the Paraclete. A man named Fulbert was convinced that this woman could be tutored by a man who lusted after her; shortly thereafter, this woman gave birth to a son named Astrolabe, and Fulbert led a mob that castrated her tutor. Marriage and prostitution are compared in the writings of, for ten points, what 12th century French feminist writer who is most famous for her correspondences with the author of <em>Sic et Non</em>, Pierre Ab\u00b4elard?", "answer": "<b> H\u00b4eloise</b> d\u2019Argenteuil", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This event was the subject of the case<em> Al-Jundi vs. Mancusi</em>, which ruled that Muslim victims had been singled out for abuse. During this event, negotiations between Russell Oswald and Elliot Barkley broke down, leaving hostages in the hands of Frank Smith. The killing of George Jackson in San Quentin inspired this event, which Governor Nelson Rockefeller was criticized for using deadly force to end. 33 people were killed fighting for better living conditions in, for ten points, what 1971 prison riot in New York?", "answer": "<b> Attica</b> prison riot", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1832, this man\u2019s bones were stolen and ritually incinerated. This man\u2019s uncle Juan debated Cardinal Giuliano Cesarini at the Council of Florence. This man ordered condemned individuals to wear sanbenitos. Sixtus IV allowed the creation of a holy office led by this man, who created tribunals in Sevilla, Saragossa and C\u00b4ordoba. Despite being descended from conversos himself, this man targeted Jews and Muslims. The marraige of Ferdinand and Isabella was recommended by, for ten points, what royal advisor and leader of the Spanish Inquisition?", "answer": "Tom\u00b4as de<b> Torquemada</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This artist painted a full-length portrait of Muhammad Dervish Khan, an ambassador sent by Tipu Sultan to France. This artist indicated the recent death of a child named</b> <b>Sophie with an empty bassinet draped with a black cloth held back by (+)</b> <b>Dauphin Louis</b> <b>Joseph. In that painting, this artist\u2019s patron wears a red dress in an attempt to repair the (*) </b> reputation that had been damaged by a painting of this artist\u2019s patron wearing a blue-feathered straw hat and a striped gold sash over a scandalously informal white gown. For ten points, name this court painter for Marie Antoinette.", "answer": "\u00b4Elisabeth Louise<b> Vige\u00b4e Le Brun</b> (accept Madame<b> Le Brun</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A ruler of these people legendarily planted a black poplar to announce that he would take the throne. One ruler of these people accidentally shot Saint Giles with an arrow. Wamba led these people, who were governed by the Code of Leovigild and the earlier Code</b> <b>of (+)</b> <b>Euric. Another leader of these people died when he fought Tariq ibn Ziyad of the</b> <b>Euric. Another leader of these people died when he fought Tariq ibn Ziyad of the</b> <b>Ummayads at the Battle of Guadalete; that man was (*)</b> <b>Ummayads at the Battle of Guadalete; that man was (*)</b> Roderic. These people held several councils of Toledo under kings like Reccared I. For ten points, name these Gothic rulers of what is now Spain, contrasted with the eastern Ostrogoths.", "answer": "<b> Visigoth</b>s (prompt on Goths)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>During this battle, the sword of the recently-killed Prince Imperial Napoleon was offered in a rejected peace treaty. This battle began with an attempt to cross the Mbilane River by Evelyn Wood\u2019s flying column and Redvers Buller\u2019s cavalry. The losing side in this battle</b> <b>was subsequently (+)</b> <b>divided into 13 chiefdoms by Garnet Wolseley, who had arrived too</b> <b>divided into 13 chiefdoms by Garnet Wolseley, who had arrived too</b> <b>late to take command. The royal kraal of (*)</b> <b>late to take command. The royal kraal of (*)</b> Cetshwayo was burned in this battle, which Lord Chelmsford hastily initiated in an attempt to salvage his reputation from a prior defeat at Isandlwana. For ten points, name this 1879 battle for the Zulu capital.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Ulundi</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In 1886, riots in this city occurred after police tried to control a crowd watching illegal eel-pulling. A silent walk in this city commemorates an event in which sacramental bread was put in a fire but remained intact. Protestant control of this city began after the 1578</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Alteratie. In 2004, filmmaker Theo van Gogh was assassinated in this city, where a</b> <b>(*)</b> dike was built in the 1930s to change the Zuider Zee into a freshwater lake. Three concentric canals encircle, for ten points, what city where Anne Frank\u2019s family was betrayed to the Nazis, the capital of the Netherlands?", "answer": "<b> Amsterdam</b> Page 10", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}